Guide to the Peirce family papers, 1856-1873
Department of Special Collections
Peirce family papers,
1856-1873
Special Collections M0202
Peirce family.
10 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Carolyn P. Brown, Miss Rosamund Peirce, and Mrs. Forrest J. Kincade, 1970.
KEY
The numbers in parentheses immediately following each name indicate the number of letters in the folder. The dates which follow indicate the earliest and latest item in the folder, but do not necessarily indicate an item from each intervening year. All folders are arranged in chronological order.
If the entry does not indicate to whom the items were sent, all letters in the folder were addressed to George H. Peirce (1837 - 1874). Any other recipients are indicated. The following abbreviations are used:
Eliza P. Eliza Mitchell Peirce (1837-1896).
Emily P. Emily Mitchell Peirce (1839-1923).
Mrs. EMP Mrs. Eliza Mitchell Peirce (d. 1887).
Mrs. GHP Lydia Ellen Eaton Peirce (1839-1903), wife of George H. Peirce.
GHP George H. Peirce (1837-1874), used only when other recipients also in folder.
Container List
- Correspondence and business papers
  - Unidentified. (20) Includes one letter from Lydia Eaton Pierce's Aunt Margie. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adams, Mary. (3) 1871 - 1872. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Adams, N.(2) May 22, 1871., Jan. 30, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adams, Sallie. (2) 1871 - 1872. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Andrews, Carrie L. (3) 1856 - 1857. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anthony, Helen V. (1) Aug. 23,to Mrs. EMP. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Arnold, S. E. (1) Sept. 5, to Mrs. EMP. (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - Barker, A. (1) 1863-74 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
  - Bigelow, Alanson. (4) 1882 - 1883,to Eliza P. and Mrs. EMP. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brown, Frank A. (3) n.d., 1856 - 1865,to GHP and Mrs. EMP. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brown, Louise Eaton. (9) n.d., 1857 - 1864,to GHP and G. Chapman, and MEW. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Byron, Lotta R. (1) April 30, 1896,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cadell, George B. (2) 1873 - 1874. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cembrano, Vicente (1) June 11, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chapin, Hattie M. (4) 1857 - 1865. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clarke, Inez L. (1) 1892,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cooke, Josiah W. (1) 1868,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cooper, W. A. (2) 1894 - 1896,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Crocker, N. Henry. (4) 1856 - 1858. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Curtis, G. M. (2) 1873. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Davis, Charles A (1) N.D. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Davis, George Hubbard. (1) 1859 (Box 1)
  - Dennis, Enoch P. (3) 1858 - 1859. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Eaton, Charles F. (1) 1867. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Eaton, Emily Craft and Percival. (1) 1892,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Eaton, James F. (2) 1894 - 1895,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Eayrs, W. N. (1) 1856. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Edwards, E. D. (37) 1863 - 1867. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Edwards, Helen M. (54) 1858-1873 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Edwards, Ogden E. (2) 1865 - 1874,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - To GHP: I. (46), 1857 - 1859. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - II. (38), 1860 - 1862. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - III. (75), 1863 - 1864. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - IV. (65), 1865 - 1867. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - V. (62), 1868 - 1870. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - VI. (49), 1871 - 1872. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - VII. (26), 1873. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fay, Ellen E. (1) 1890,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Foster, Frederick. (5) 1873 - 1874. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Foster, John S. (1) 1850. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Foulerton, I. (1) 1859. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Franklin Literary Association. (1) 1856. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - French, M. Azubah. (2) 1857. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - French, Charles E. (1) 1857(see addition)
  - French, John. I. (56), 1856 - 1865. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - II. (28), 1866 - 1873. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Graves, Peirce W. (2) 1857 - 1858. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Green, E. H. (2) 1862 - 1863. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Greene, Mathilde Meyer. (3) 1895,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Heald, Frank. (1) 1874,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Heron, F. Griswold. (1) 1873,to Commendatore Pantaleone. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Hobart, David Kimball. (33) 1856 - 1861. Oct. 30, 1860note with letter by John J. French enclosed. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hodges, E. A. (1) 1880,to Mrs. EMP. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Howe, William. (2) 1892 - 1895,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Howell, Mrs. George F. (1) 1895,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hoyt, Mrs. A. M. (1) August 25,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Hunter, Rosalie. (14) 1857-1860, 1868. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Huntington, A. (2) 1868). (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Huntington, C. L. (1) n.d.,to Mrs. EMP. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Kinsman, W. L. (2) 1862. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Kirkpatrick, H. R. (1) 1891,to Emily P. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Langer, Gertrude F. (1) 1892,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Laur, ------. (2) 1874,to Mrs. EMP. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Laurence, A. W. (12) n.d., 1883,to Eliza P. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Laurence, C. B. (1) 1879,to Charles F. Wyman. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Lemper, Anna. (1) 1868. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Lockwood, R. D. (2) 1856 - 1857. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Manning, Anna R. (1) n.d.,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Manning, Helen. (1) 1892,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Minns, Thomas. (3) 1856 - 1858. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mitchell, Albert. (1) 1868. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mitchell, Charles. (6) 1856 - 1857. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Mitchell, Emily P. (2) 1856 - 1857.GHP's aunt. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mitchell, Nathaniel. I. Correspondence to GHP, (75) 1857 - 1868. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - II. - IV. General business papers, including accounts, miscellaneous correspindence, stock certificates, promissory notes, legal papers. (Box 4, Folder 16, Folder 17, Folder 18)
  - V. Bills. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - VI. Dorrance, Oliver B., dealings with. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - VII. Hallowell Steam Mill Property. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - VIII. Loring, David W., dealings with. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - IX. Maine Quarry Association. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - X. Resolutions, Commissions, Powers. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mitchell, Susan P. (4) 1856 - 1859. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Mitchell, Willie P. (1) 1856. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Morton, Lizzie S. (2) 1856 - 1857. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mugford, C. P. (1) 1857. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Nicholson, Charles W. (2) 1872,to Ogden E. Edwards. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Noyes, Marion. (1) 1880,to Mrs. EMP. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Palmer, Charles Ray. (2) 1892 - 1896,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Palmer, Hattie (Mrs. Charles Ray). (1) 1892,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Palmer, Horatio Nelson. (3) 1874 - 1878,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - To GHP: I. (47) 1858 - 1861. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - II. (28) 1862. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - III. (51) 1863. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - IV. (34) 1864 - 1865. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - V. (40) 1866 - 1867. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - VI. (30) 1868. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - VII. (32) 1869 - 1870. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - VIII. (53) 1871 - 1873. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Peirce, Abby C. (2) 1860 - 1864. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Peirce, Caroline P. (3) 1868 - 1874,to, Mr. and Mrs. GHP. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Peirce, Eliza Mitchell (Mrs. EMP). (1) n.d.,to Mr. and Mrs. GHP. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - To GHP: I. (64) 1856 - 1859. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - II. (69) 1860 - 1862. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - III. (82) 1863 - 1866. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - IV. (83) 1867 - 1870. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - V. (51) 1871 - 1873. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Bills, 1884 - 1886. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Peirce, Eliza. (sister of GHP). (33) 1850 - 1880,to Mrs. EMP and Emily P. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - To GHP: I. (75) 1856 - 1861. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - II. (77) 1862 - 1869. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Peirce, Eliza Philips. (1) 1862. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Peirce, Emily Mitchell. (c. 75) Written from Europe to Mrs. EMP and Eliza P. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - To GHP: I. (80) 1856 - 1861. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - II. (88) 1862 - 1866. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - III. (56) 1867 - 1870. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - IV. (33) 1871 - 1873. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - [UNK] (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - [UNK] (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - [UNK] (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - [UNK] (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - [UNK] (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - [UNK] (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - [UNK] (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - [UNK] (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - [UNK] (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - [UNK]
  - [UNK]
  - [UNK] (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Peirce, William Putnam. (28) 1856 - 1859. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Pickford, C.R.P. (3) 1873. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Pollard, Samuel S. (12) 1856 - 1862. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Putnam, George D. (9) 1856 - 1863. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Ranlett, Charles A. Jr. (1) 1873. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Reed, T. Frank. (80) 1856 - 1872. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Richards, Henry. (15) 1856 - 1868. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Sage, Edward. (20) 1862 - 1868. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Sampson, Martin W. (1) 1896,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - San Jacintor, pursor of the. (1) n.d. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Sietterrlaeur, Ino. (1) 1858 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Smith, Charles C. (1) 1856. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Stedman, Grace. (1) 1892,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Stone, Eliza J. (1) 1872. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Trott, Charles H. (8) 1856 - 1859. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Tucker, Richard Dalton. I. (71) 1858 - 1866. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - II. (41) 1867 - 1868. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - III. (113) 1869 - 1873. (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Van Rensselaer, P. S. (1) 1868. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - von Glehn, E. (1) 1873. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Walker, Marcus. (1) 1856. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Ware, Sarah E. (1) 1863. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Weld, Daniel. (1) 1871. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Whipple, E. K. (1) May 3to Mrs. GHP. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Williams, Charles F. (2) 1858. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Williams, William B. (20) 1860 - 1867. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Wilson, Lucy L. (1) 1892,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Worthington, Thomas. (1) 1892,to George J. P. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Worthington, Nellie. (1) 1892,to Mrs. GHP. (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Wyman, Charles. (8) 1873 - 1874,to Mrs. GHP, Mrs. EMP. (Box 11, Folder 12)
    (see addition list)
    - To GHP: I. (120) 1856 - 1866. (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - To GHP: II. (138) 1867 - 1874. (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Wyman, Margaret Eaton. (12) 1856 - 1873. (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Books and Ledgers
  - Peele, Hubbell and Co. Printed press book, with enclosed business circulars.
    - I. 1856 - 1863. (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - II. 1864 - 1870. (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - III. 1872 - 1873(circulars only). (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Peirce, George H. Correspondence copybook and abstracts of incoming Peele, Hubbell and Co. mail; diary.
    - I. Diary, June - October 1856. (Box 12, Folder 4a)
    - II. Copybook, 1868 - September 1869. (Box 12, Folder 4b)
    - III. September 1869 - April 1871. (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - IV. May 1871 - August 1872. (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - V. August 1872 - December 1873. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Peirce, George H. Account Books.
    - I. Business accounts (private ventures). (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - II. Private accounts. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Book of pro forma invoices and price computation tables. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Oversize ledger. Business accounts. 1866 - 1873. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Notebooks.
    - I. Contains a few letters and bible verses learned by young George J. Peirce
    - II. c. 1889;essays and notes.
    - III. c. 1889 - 1890;notes on animal morphology. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Notebooks. Mrs. George H. Peirce.
    - I. Recipes; II. Expense accounts; III. Verse. IV, Misc. Notes (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Book. Philippine tariffs; dated November 21, 1860. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Bennett's Handbook For Norway For 1870. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Mercantile Review (English and Spanish). multiple copies 10/31/1873; 11/14/1873; 11/28/1873; 12/12/1873. (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous and Oversize
  - Student Visa issued to George P. Peirce, 1893. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Christmas cards. Late 19th. century. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Miscellany, including: (Box Box 15)
    - (a) European trip (Box Box 16)
    - (b) verse fragments. (Box Box 17)
  - 1. English High School Association, Boston, Massachusetts. Life Membership certificate, May 1, 1872. (Othertype oversize file)
  - 2. Oversize photo albums; two of Manila and Philippines; one of HongKong, Canton, Macao, Peking. (Othertype oversize file)
  - 3. Oversize map of Manila. (Othertype oversize file)
  - 4. Issustracion Filipina, various issues, 1859 - 1860. (Othertype oversize file)
  - 5. Portrait of woman, in gilt frame.
  - 6. Water colors (4), depicting Manila earthquake. (Othertype oversize file)
  - 7. Paperweight. Metal horse.
    in MSS Division (for use of desk)
  - 8. Seal. Ivory, in leather case.
  - 9. Money pouches (3), leather
  - 10. Metal nib pen.
  - 11. Copper printing plate for business card of GHP.
  - 12. Magnifying glass without handle.
    [UNK] MSS Division (for use at desk)
  - 13. Embroidered pouch.
  - 14. Copper printing plate, with some printed cards, of Mrs. GHP.
  - 15. Keys (2); wax seal in envelope.
  - 16. Money purse, blue knit.
  - 17. Glasses, wire rim (4), with cases.
  - 18. Photos of curtoons (Folder folder, Box box 14/9)
  - Name slips (Folder folder)
  - Clippings (Folder folder)
  - Fragments:
    - Business correspondence. (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Diary. (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Address Book. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Passports:
    - George H. Peirce, 1873.(Issued by Philippines). (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Lydia E. Peirce, 1874.(Issued by United States). (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Receipts. (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Bills. (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Invoice files. (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Business Circulars. (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Business cards. (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Copybook entries. Telegrams. (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Deeds. (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Peirce Family Crest. (Box 18, Folder 13)
ADDITION AT END
(originals in safe)
- 4-11-71Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3 sides
- 5-5-71Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 9-21-71Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 10-21-71Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 11-21-71Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 3-20-73Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 5-6-73Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 6-19-73Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 10-19/20-58Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 2 fragment
- 2-21/27-60Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 2 fragment
- 8-26-61Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 + (copy) 1/2 sheet
- 10-25-61Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 5 25-63Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 1-29-64Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 5-10-64Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 11-10-64Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 11-25-64Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 4-11-65Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 11-14-65Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 5-4-66Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 5-18-66Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4
- 6-15-1857Boston Charles G. French to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 10-21-1867Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 3-24-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 4-9-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 5-22-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 6-19-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 7-3-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 2 sides
- 7-17-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 2 sides
- 10-22-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 11-6-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 11-20-1868Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 2-12-1869Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 2-20-1869Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 3-12-1869Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 2 sides
- 4-9-1869Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 5-21-1869Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 7-2-1869Boston Char. F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 7-29-1864Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 4 sides
- 9-23-1869Boston, 3 sides
- 10-7-69Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 11-19-69Boston Charles F. Wyman to Geo. H. Pierce, 3
- 12-2-69, 4
- 2-21-70Boston, 3
- 7-15-70, 2 (faded)
- 9-22-70, 3
- 10-7-70, 3
- 10-22-70, 3
- 2-10-71, 4